Finding Aid for the Mary Helen Clark Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Mary Helen Clark Papers
1928-1946
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0082
Biography/History
Mary Helen Clark [1902-1987] was born in Paris, Kentucky. She received her B.A. from Kentucky Wesleyan College and an M.A. from Columbia University. She did graduate work at the University of Kentucky, Scarritt and Peabody Colleges, and Cambridge University, England. She taught in the public schools of Kentucky and Florida before going to Brazil as a missionary in August 1928.
Miss Clark served at Bennett College, Rio de Janeiro, and at the Isabela Hendrix College in Belo Horizonte before being transferred to the Colegio Americano in Porto Alegre, Rio Grande do Sul, where she was appointed principal. In addition to her educational work, she took the lead in community service at the time of the disastrous floods of 1964 when the school took in, fed, and clothed over 100 disaster victims. She received the highest honor from the City Council of Porto Alegre – the title of “Citizen of Porto Alegre.”
She returned to the United States in 1968, moving to Nashville, Tennessee, where her sister Blanche Henry Clark Weaver resided.
Scope and Contents
This .42 linear feet collection, 33 file folders, contains correspondence from Mary Helen Clark to her family from 1928-1946, when she lived in Brazil. It also contains correspondence from Blanche Henry Clark to her family during her visit to Brazil in 1932 to visit her sister. The letters are arranged chronologically, and give detailed accounts of Mary Helen’s days in Brazil. The letters provide first-hand accounts of Latin-American foods, behaviors, language and customs of the people and the politics of the times.
- Correspondence – Mary Helen Clark to Family
  - August – December 1928
  - January – June 1929
  - July – December 1929
  - January – June 1930
  - July – December 1930
  - January – June 1931
  - July – December 1931
  - January – June 1932
  - July – December 1932
  - January – June 1933
  - July – December 1933
  - ***** There is no correspondence for 1934 *****
  - January – June 1935
  - July – December 1935
  - January – June 1936
  - July – December 1936
  - January – June 1937
  - July – December 1937
  - January – June 1938
  - July – December 1938
  - January – June 1939
  - July – December 1939
  - January – May 1940
  - March – June 1941
  - July – December 1941
  - January – June 1942
  - July – December 1942
  - January – June 1943
  - July – December 1943
  - January – December 1944
  - April – December 1945
  - March – May 1946
  - Undated
- Correspondence – Blanche Henry Clark to Family
  - 1932